Guide to the New England Women Ministers Association Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
New England Women Ministers Association Records
1952-1998
RG 303
Yale University Divinity School Library
2
(3 boxes; 1 oversize box)
Minutes, reports, correspondence, publications, and collected material document the work of the New England Women Ministers Association, an organization that sought to provide support and strengthen ties between its members.
New England Women Ministers Association
History
Oral tradition indicates that in 1922 a group of women ministers gathered at Bangor Theological Seminary in an effort to form a continuing fellowship. The organizing meeting of New England Women Ministers Association was in Keene, New Hampshire, in May 1938. For several years thereafter the group met annually one day of the week of the Rural Church Workers Conference at Ocean Park, Maine. The group adopted a more formal structure in 1952 with the election of a slate of officers. The organization's focus remained on the annual meeting at which issues of common interest were discussed. In 1959 a constitution was adopted, formalizing the purpose of the group since its inception: to strengthen the ties that bind women ministers together in the Christian ministry; to encourage competent and consecrated women to consider the vocation of ministry. A subsequent revision in 1982 refined the purpose: to strengthen the ties that bind women in ministry; to encourage and support one another; to provide role models; and to affirm and enhance the chosen vocation of women ministers. New England Women Ministers Association continued its tradition of providing a time of retreat and reflection through the programs scheduled at the annual meeting.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Deposited in Andover Newton Theological School collection in 1992, transferred to Yale Divinity Library in 2017
Scope and Contents
Minutes, reports, correspondence, publications, and collected material document the work of the New England Women Ministers Association.
Arrangement
Organized into five series:
Series I. Legal Records
Series II. Administration Records
Series III. Ad Hoc Committees
Series IV. Publications
Series V. Special Events and Projects
Series VI. Regional Chapters
Women clergy; New England Women Ministers Association
- Legal Records, Series I
  - Constitutions, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Listed in the original finding aid as follows: 04/00/1959 Tentative, First Draft; 04/15/1959 As adopted; 04/26/1962 Including revisions suggested April 26, 1962 at Annual Meeting (2 versions); 04/16/1964 Changes proposed in the NEWMA Constitution at the 1964 Annual Meeting, to be voted on at the 1965 meeting; 04/00/1982 Proposed Revised Constitution; 04/22/1982 Approved at Annual Meeting, April 22, 1982; 04/25/1991 Approved at Annual Meeting, April 25, 1991; 04/30/1992 Changes; 04/30/1992 Approved at Annual Meeting, April 30, 1992; 04/29/1993 Approved at Annual Meeting, April 29, 1993; Recommended Changes to the Constitution
- Administration Records, Series II
  - Minutes, reports, membership records
    - President reports, 1990-1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Vice-President reports, 1990-1991, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Membership Registrar reports, 1976, 1983-1986, 1991-1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Supporting documents, including: job description, membership applications, procedure, sample welcome letter, 1982-1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Address and membership lists, 1959-1999, no date (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Minutes of annual meetings and supporting documents, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Minutes of annual meetings and supporting documents, 1955-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Minutes of annual meetings and supporting documents, 1981-1998 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence, including circular letters, 1954-1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Correspondents include: Betsy Sowers, Gretchen Hall, Margaret Morton, Dorothy Pease, Eva Henderson, Miriam Higgins, Evelyn Grindle, Laura Ingler, Ruth E. Thompson, Sophia Fahs, Helen Terkelsen, Edith Northrop, Beryl Capewell, Marion Stickney, Lillian Standish, Nancy Hildonen, Miriam Ackor, Gladys York, John H. Chafee, Miriam Eckard, Jacqueline Mills, Ruth Weber, Eunice Shaw Bull, Helen Zigmund, Polly Laughland, Drucilla Schneiderheinze, Ida Folsom, Elsie Gibson, Sarah A. Edwards
    - Correspondence, including circular letters, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Correspondents include: Gretchen Hall, Frances Knerr Thorne, Marja Coons, Paul Mahowald S.J., Jo-an Bott, Cathy Narowitz, Evelyn Grindle, Elsie Gibson, Marie Tolander, Diane Pierce, Valerie Tregger, Gay Godfrey, Helen Zigmund, Gerrie Brown, Sr. Mary T. Coffey, Harriet Newman, Betsy Sowers, Mary C. Clapp, Marilyn Cusick, Jean Reidel, Ann Duffy, Pat Halsall, Jamie Gustafson
    - Correspondence, including circular letters, 1982-1997 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Correspondents include: Carole Etzler, Sharon Smith Viles, Peg Jacobs, Olivia Hayes, Sarah Davis Smith, Lucy Brady, Ann B. Day, Franny Nudelman, Cynthia L. Walton, Alice M. Ling, Sandra Ragle, Linnea Prefontaine, Barbara Breen, Barbara Silk, Elizabeth Frazier, Joyce Quinn Blum, Brenda Moulton
  - Treasurer records
    - Annual reports, 1969-1998 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Supporting documents, 1970-1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Supporting documents, 1995-1998 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Historian records
    - Historical notes and reports, 1975-1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Historical news clippings, 1949-1997 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
    - Historical writings by members, 1959-1984 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Published and unpublished material. Authors include: Gretchen Hall, Gladys D. York, Sophia Lyon Fahs, S. Elizabeth Goodrich, Elsie Gibson, Merle H. Mason, Cecelia Belanger
    - Subject-related articles collected by historian, 1968-1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Scrapbook of clippings and documents collected by NEWMA historian, 1965-1973 (Box OV1)
  - Publicity records
    - Press releases, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Annual reports, 1994, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee
    - Minutes, 1962, 1970, 1978, 1980, 1985, 1986, 1991-1998 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Supporting documents, 1980-1998 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Ad Hoc Committees, Series III
  - Committee for the Exploration of Discrimination Against Women in the Ministry
    - Statement of purpose and membership list, 1971 April 15 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Suggested letter to be sent to women ministers in New England, 1971 May 3 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Publications, Series IV
  - News Sheet, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Summer Activities of the NEWMA Network, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Flyers, Newsletters, etc., 1982-1998 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Special Events and Projects, Series V
  - Survey of NEWMA members, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Program: Spirituality and the Woman Minister, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Christmas card exchange, 1982-1984 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - 50th anniversary celebration, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Regional Chapters, Series VI
  - Massachusetts: Evaluation of workshop "Blessed are the Peacemakers" (1981); publicity flyer (1984), 1981, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Vermont: Program, events for 1981; letter from Cynthia L. Walton; notice of meeting (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous material, primarily related to non-NEWMA events (Box 3, Folder 14-15)